<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lying spirit and false aspertions turned home again, or, An answer to two reviling letters about the peoples right to tythes sent to the people call'd Quakers in the Vail of Bellvier by Clement Nedham, a Presbyterian, who writes himself, a farmer in the county of Leicester : wherein I have shew'd according to scriptures, what spirit it was that brought up tythes among the Christians, so call'd : and that those that brought them up since Christ put an end to them were not in their right senses, but were made drunk by drinking of that spirit of error that made them do they knew not what, and consequently their examples not to be followed : with an addition, shewing, that the impropriator hath less right to tythes then the poor or priest, if less can be : with a few words in love to all those that send their sons to those places called universities, with an intent to make them ministers : also a copy of a letter sent to G.N. in manuscript, wherein his unhansom and unchristian-like dealings may be seen : with a short postcript to the reader / by J.W. ...</title>
            <author>Willsford, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40124</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18722591</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18722591</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108218</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66530)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108218)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1662:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lying spirit and false aspertions turned home again, or, An answer to two reviling letters about the peoples right to tythes sent to the people call'd Quakers in the Vail of Bellvier by Clement Nedham, a Presbyterian, who writes himself, a farmer in the county of Leicester : wherein I have shew'd according to scriptures, what spirit it was that brought up tythes among the Christians, so call'd : and that those that brought them up since Christ put an end to them were not in their right senses, but were made drunk by drinking of that spirit of error that made them do they knew not what, and consequently their examples not to be followed : with an addition, shewing, that the impropriator hath less right to tythes then the poor or priest, if less can be : with a few words in love to all those that send their sons to those places called universities, with an intent to make them ministers : also a copy of a letter sent to G.N. in manuscript, wherein his unhansom and unchristian-like dealings may be seen : with a short postcript to the reader / by J.W. ...</title>
                  <author>Willsford, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bevan-Naish Collection.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108218:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108218:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Lying Spirit AND FALSE ASPERTIONS Turned home again. Or an Anſwer to two Reviling Letters about the <hi>Peoples Right to Tythes,</hi> ſent to the People call'd <hi>Quakers</hi> in the Vail of <hi>Bellvier</hi> by <hi>Clement Nedham,</hi> a <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> who writes himſelf, <hi>A Farmer in the County of</hi> Leiceſter. Wherein I have ſhew'd according to Scriptures, what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit it was that brought up <hi>Tythes</hi> among the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo call'd. And that thoſe that brought them up ſince Chriſt put an End to them were not in their Right Senſes, but were made Drunk by drinking of that ſpirit of error that made them do they knew not what, and conſequently their Examples not to be followed. With an <hi>Addition,</hi> ſhewing, That the <hi>Impropriator</hi> hath leſs Right to <hi>Tythes</hi> then the <hi>Poor</hi> or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> if leſs can be. With a few Words in Love to all thoſe that ſend their Sons to thoſe Places called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> with an Intent to make them <hi>Miniſters.</hi> Alſo a Copy of a Letter ſent to <hi>G. N.</hi> in manuſcript, wherein his Unhanſom and Unchriſtian-like Dealings may be ſeen. With a ſhort Poſtſcript to the Reader <hi>By</hi> J. W. <hi>a Lover of Truth and all Men's Souls,</hi> Whoſe outward Being is in the Vail of <hi>Bellvier,</hi> and County of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Wherefore the Lord ſaid, <hi>Foraſmuch as this People draw near me with their Mouthes, and with their Lips do Honour me, but have removed their Hearts for from me, and their Fear towards me is taught by the Precepts of Men; therefore behold I will proceed to do a Marvelous Work amongst this People, even a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous Work and a Wonder: For the Wiſdom of their Wiſe Men ſhall periſh, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding of their Prudent Men ſhall be hid. For it is written, I will destroy the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, and bring to nothing the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding of the Prudent,</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 29.13, 14, 1 Cor. 1.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:108218:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:108218:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Was not forward in meddling with this Giant, who boaſted and domineered over me; bad it not been for the Truth's ſake I could have been ſilent; but the Love that I bear to it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains me to bear my Teſtimony (though not with inticing words of Man's Wiſdom) againſt Deceit and Oppreſſion: And ſo I deſire thee to mind the Inſpiration of the Almighty, for that gives an Underſtanding: <hi>It is the Spirit that reveals the deep Things of God, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>2.</hi> And as thou turneſt thy Mind inwards, to be acquainted with its Teachings, it will let thee ſee the Way that a Wafaring Man, though a Fool, cannot err in; and ſo thou wilt come to ſee the Rice, Ground, Bottom and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of things, and that is the Right Way to begin to build: and not to build upon <hi>Popiſh</hi> Authors, or to take Drunken Men for thy Example; I mean ſuch as were Drunk by drinking that ſpirit of Error that led from God into an Heap of Confuſion, which is <hi>Babylon:</hi> And by the Spirit of Truth thou mayſt ſee, as thou mindſt, what it was that ſtrove with the Old World before the outward Law was added, which Law was added becauſe of Tranſgreſſion, <hi>&amp; was to continue until the fulneſs of Time, that God ſent his Son a Light into the World, to end the Types and Shadows, Tythes and Offerings, that that Law required.</hi> So Reader, I deſire thee to take notice, <hi>That Chriſt put an End to Tythes;</hi> and who brought them up
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108218:3"/>again in this following Treatiſe I hope thou mayſt ſee, even him whoſe <hi>Coming is after the Working of Satan, with all Power, Signs and Lying Wonders, 2</hi> Theſ. <hi>2.</hi> (Haſt thou not heard of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> working Miracles) [Mark] He had Power; <hi>What Power,</hi> may ſome ſay? I anſwer, Power to deceive and beguile by his Signs and Lying Wonders, and then to make Laws for the Continuance and Upholding of that which he had gotten by Deceit. And people, when I ſpeak of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Antichriſt</hi> or <hi>Beaſt,</hi> I mean that ſpirit of Error that led from God; for it hath ſeveral Names; becauſe of its ſeveral wayes of workings; Satan hath many Wiles, and ſo he hath many Names: And there are but two Spirits in the Ground, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth, and the ſpirit of Error; and Chriſt is the Truth, who hath many Names and Offices, all which is to lead into a Holy Life; but the ſpirit of Error leads into an Unholy Life; ſo they may be known by their Workings in Man and Woman: And Happy are all they that come to be redeemed from under the Power of Satan, Beaſt and Antichriſt in themſelves; for there they are while people live in Sin, and there their Fall muſt be: For Chriſt hath determined to bind the Strong Man armed, and to caſt him out of the Houſe, and to take the Poſſeſſion, himſelf: And ſo people, we are not ſpeaking of the Fall of Kings and Rulers from their Thrones of Juſtice; but of the Fall of the Beaſt, Whore and Antichriſt in Man and Woman; and this will hurt none, to have that deſtroyed which keeps from God. And therefore I exhort all that love their own Souols, to wait low in their Minds, that they may feel Chriſt Jeſus exerciſing his Offices in them, which is to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, and to bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:108218:3"/>
            <head>THE Lying Spirit AND FALSE ASPERTIONS Turned Home again. OR An Anſwer to Two Reviling Letters about the <hi>Peoples Right to Tythes,</hi> ſent to the People call'd <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in the <hi>Vail</hi> of <hi>Bellvier</hi> by <hi>Clement Nedham,</hi> a <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> who writes himſelf, <hi>A Farmer in the County of</hi> Leiceſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Friend</hi> Nedham,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough thy <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> be the laſt, yet it concerns my firſt Letter ſent to thee: I might ſay ſomething to thy Reviling Words in it, but having written ſomething to thee in a Letter, and knowing it was the Practice of the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and <hi>out-ſide Profeſſors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 7.49.</note> to <hi>Revile the Children of Light,</hi> and to count them <hi>ſuch as knew not the Law,</hi> at preſent I may paſs them by; only take notice of this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108218:4"/>by the way, That if I had been ſo ignorant, as in thy Eyes I ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be, it had been thy place to have written or ſpoken ſomething to me in particular; that had been the beſt way for thee to have mannaged thy Deſign to have convinced me of my Error, if in one I had been; but thou haſt directed thy Reviling Words to others, and not a word to me in particular; wherein thou haſt manifeſted thy Folly and Ignorance in mannaging thy Deſign; but it is like my <hi>Confidence</hi> offended thee: yet I muſt tell thee, <hi>I am as Confident as ever I was, yea, and more Confirmed;</hi> for ſince thou didſt write thy Reviling Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets the Lord hath opened my Underſtanding more then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to ſee beyond thy Traſh and <hi>Rome</hi>'s Trumpery, inſomuch that I have Cauſe to ſay as Chriſt ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>I thank thee, O Father, who haſt hid theſe things from the VViſe and Prudent, and haſt revealed them to Babes and Sucklings:</hi> And in this is that Scripture fulfilled that ſaith, <hi>All things work together for Good to them that love God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as concerning thy new ſtart-up Queſtion, which thou ſayſt, <hi>I writ nothing at all unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> If the Myſteries of the Kingdom had not been hid from the Wiſe and Prudent in their own Eyes, as in all Ages they were, thou mighteſt have ſeen that I had written ſomething to the Subſtance of thy Matter: <hi>But the Blind cannot ſee, nor the Deaf Adder hear, although the Charmer charm never ſo wiſely.</hi> And further, as concerning thy Queſtion; Chriſt himſelf did not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes anſwer the Queſtions that thy Brethren the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, Chief Prieſts,</hi> and thoſe who thought they had the Law on their ſides, asked him, when they thought to enfnare him; but ſometimes he anſwered one Queſtion by asking another, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.29. and thou thy ſelf haſt ſeem'd to do ſo in thy Book. And now whether thy Queſtion about the People's Right to Tythes may not be anſwered with a Juſt Demand from thee, <hi>What Right the People of thy Perſwaſion had to take away the Biſhops Lands from them?</hi> If thou ſayeſt, <hi>The Biſhops had no Right to them, becauſe contrary to the Practice of the Biſhops in the Primitive Times, who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108218:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>were not to be Covetous, nor given to Filthy Lucre,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. The ſame ſay we by the Prieſts concerning Tythes.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing thou haſt made thy ſelf ſo buſie, as few I think might worſe have done, I might proceed to ask thee, <hi>What Right thou or the People of thy Perſwaſion had to Sell or Buy ſome men's Free-Lands? And whether the King and his Laws have not been favourable to thee and ſome of thy Party?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further concerning thy Queſtion; Do not thoſe that buy Land buy every Part and Parcel, with all that thereunto belongs? And are they tyed by their Deeds to pay their Tenths, yea, or nay? If nay, how are they Thieves and Robbers for detaining that which they never came in Covenant with any to pay? And as to the Intents of Every Buyer and Seller, thou haſt ſtretched too far; For how knoweſt thou the Intents of thoſe that ſold or bought Land ſome Hundreds of years ſince, further then their Deeds or Writings make mention? And we performing our Covenants ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Deeds and Leaſes, are clear from thy ſalfe Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:108218:5"/>
               <p>I Have taken notice of thy ſecond Letter, and there I find, that thou ſleighteſt thoſe thou counteſt to have much more Reaſon then I have, as much or more then thou doſt me (in theſe words) thou ſayeſt, <hi>Thou art to Thank that Author for thy Information of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Kings, that made Laws for the Payment of Tythes:</hi> To which thou art pleaſed to make Five Demands, but being anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>T. R.</hi> I ſhall not need to meddle with them at preſent; for my Intent is to ſpeak to the Ground of the Matter, and ſo I take notice of thy following words; thou ſayeſt, <hi>Thou art ſtill to thank the ſame Author for thy Information, that King</hi> Steven <hi>by his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gave Tenths for the Pardon of his Sins; and the like by</hi> Ralph <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Chicheſter, <hi>for the Health of his Soul; and that</hi> Walter Clifford, <hi>in the time of King</hi> John, <hi>gave the Tenths of</hi> Hammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <hi>for the Health of his Father's Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, for thy better Information, firſt conſider, That Chriſt Jeſus, the pure Law-giver, was the End of that Law that gave Tythes; ſecondly, conſider what ſpirit was got up when thoſe things above mentioned were done. For Proof of the firſt I might preduce many Scriptures; but I deſire thee and thy Reader to take notice of a few, and peruſe them at your Leiſures, <hi>Romans</hi> 10.4. <hi>Galatians</hi> 3.10, 11, 12, 13, 19. Wherefore then ſerveth the Law? <hi>It was added becauſe of Tranſgreſſion, till the Seed ſhould come to whom the Promiſe was made:</hi> Further, ſee <hi>Hebrews</hi> Chap. 7, 8, 9.</p>
               <p>And as to the ſecond, which is to ſhew what Spirit was got up when theſe things above mentioned were done; conſider what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. he Exhorted the Elders of the Church, <hi>To take heed unto themſelves, and to all the Flock over the which the Holy Ghoſt had made them Over-ſeers;</hi> for he ſaid, <hi>That after his Departure grievous Wolves ſhould enter in among them, not ſparing the Flock: Alſo, of your own ſelves</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>ſhall Men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them.</hi> And
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108218:5"/>in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. he ſaid, <hi>The Myſtery of Iniquity doth already work, only he who now letteth will let until he be taken out of the way; then ſhall that wicked one be revealed, whom the Lord ſhall Comſume with the Spirit of his Mouth, and deſtroy with the Brightneſs of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming:</hi> So take notice, the Apoſtle foretold of the coming up of the Myſtery of Iniquity, and of its being conſumed and deſtroyed again by the Brightneſs of the Lord's Coming. In 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. the Apoſtle ſpake of ſome, <hi>that ſhould depart from the Faith, giving heed to Seducing Spirits and Doctrings of Devils, forbidding to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and commanding to abſtain from Meats:</hi> And doſt thou think the Apoſtle did not ſee the riſe of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> or Falſe Church, when he ſpake theſe words. Further, <hi>Paul</hi> writ to <hi>Titus, Not to give heed to</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Fables and Commandments of Men, that turn from the Truth:</hi> And was not Tythes a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Type when ended by Chriſt? And did not they that turned unto them turn from the Truth? which would be a Denying Chriſt come in the Fleſh. Anſwer in Plaineneſs; elſe would they have given them for the Health of their own Souls, or their Fathers, or for the Pardon of their Sins. Alſo <hi>Jude</hi> ſpake of certain men <hi>that were crept in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares</hi> (ſo they were crept in then) <hi>Wo unto them,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for they are gone in the way of</hi> Cain (mark, they were gone) <hi>and run greedily after the Error of</hi> Balaam <hi>for Reward.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> ſaw ſomething that was not well in the Church of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and therefore he exhorted them, <hi>To Repent, and do their Firſt Works</hi> (mark, their Firſt Works) and he exhorted ſome of them to their <hi>Firſt Love.</hi> And how often did <hi>Paul</hi> exhort the Church to <hi>ſtand faſt,</hi> fore-ſeeing the Danger of their being drawn aſide?</p>
               <p>Oh that people rightly ſaw the Drift of the holy Apoſtles in theſe things, which was to keep them to the Faith once delivered to the Saints, and to walk as they had them for an Example; and not to take the Apoſtatized <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for their Examples: And how mightily did <hi>Paul</hi> ſtrive to keep the <hi>Galatians</hi> from the Works of the Law: And were or Tythes of Work of the Law? and never in uſe amongſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whilſt they kept their Firſt State. See what <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith 2 Epiſt. 2.1, 2, 3. I might produce many Scriptures to prove that the Apoſtles fore-ſaw a Falling away;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108218:6"/>but ſee what <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 2 Epiſt. 2. <hi>Little Children, it is the Laſt Times; as ye have heard that Antichriſt ſhould come, even now are there many Antichriſts:</hi> And is not that Antichriſt that is contrary to Chriſt, the Everlaſting High Prieſt, <hi>not made after the Law of a Carnal Commandment, but after the Power of an endleſs Life;</hi> who put an End to Tythes and Offerings, and offered himſelf once for all. And further, <hi>John</hi> exhorted the Church <hi>to that they had in the Beginning, even to the Anointing within, to preſerve them out of the Snares of Antichriſt,</hi> becauſe he ſaw him working in a Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; before whoſe time I do not find that Tythes came up in this laſt Age. Oh! How lovingly did <hi>John</hi> write unto them? ſaying, <hi>Little Children abide in him.</hi> Further, ſee what <hi>John</hi> ſaid in the <hi>Revelations</hi> Chap. 13. he ſaid, <hi>He ſaw a Beaſt coming up out of the Earth, and he had two Horns like a Lamb, and he ſpake as a Dragon, and he exerciſeth all the Power of the firſt Beaſt;</hi> And what was the firſt Beaſt? was it not that Spirit that was got up among the <hi>Heathen Emperors,</hi> when they perſecuted the <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> And afterwards, when the ſecond Beaſt aroſe, which had two Horns like a Lamb, did not the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute one another, and the <hi>Pope</hi> get over the Kings and Emperors? And this <hi>Beaſt wrought Miracles;</hi> Here the <hi>Papiſts</hi> may ſee from whence their <hi>Miracles</hi> came: <hi>And this Beaſt, that came up like a Lamb</hi> (mark, mildly by Perſwaſion, yet at laſt) <hi>cauſeth all both Small and Great, Rich and Poor, Free and Bond to receive a Mark in their Right-hand, or in their Foreheads; and that no Man might Buy or Sell, ſave he that had the Mark or the Name of the Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now <hi>C. N.</hi> ſee what Laws thou <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſo ſtrongly pleadeſt for; Is it not ſo in moſt places now, that a Man can hardly buy, ſell, or Trade with any thing, but the <hi>Prieſt</hi> will look for a Tenth Part, if not for a Seventh of many things, which need not be named, ſeeing the poor Country People, that labour hard for what they have know ſo well how Coverous the <hi>Prieſt</hi> is, that if he hears the Sow has pigged, away goes he, or ſends, to ſee what is for him, or when the Ewe has lambed; but he will make them keep them till they be fit for his Mouth; likewiſe when the Sheep are ſheared, Corn and Apples ready: And doſt not thou
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108218:6"/>plead right by the Beaſts Law? But what Example is there in Scripture for theſe things? This is more then the <hi>Tenths of Lands.</hi> But thou ſayeſt, <hi>It is known to every Buyer and Seller;</hi> and thou ſeemeſt as if thou wouldſt have none buy or Sell, where the Beaſt hath power but thoſe that can pay theſe things: But is it not a Mark, that thoſe that pay and plead for them are Upholders of Antichriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?<note place="margin">The Waters where the Whore ſitteth are Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Multitudes, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Tongues.</note> 
                  <hi>John</hi> numbred the dayes of the Beaſt, Verſ. 18. contrary to thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; for thou pleadeſt as if his Raign might never have an End: But <hi>John</hi> ſpake further of the Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of the Beaſt, and ſaid, <hi>If any Man worſhippen him or his Image, or received his Mark, they ſhould drink of the Wine of the VVrath of God,</hi> Rev. 14. He ſaid further in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. <hi>There came one of the Seven Angels, which had the Seven Vials, and talked with me, ſaying unto me, Come hither, I will ſhew thee the Judgment of the Great VVhore, that ſitteth upon many VVaters, with whom the Kings of the Earth has committed Fornication, and the Inhabitants of the Earth have been made Drunk with the Wine of her Fornication.</hi> And how are Men when they are drank? Are they not beſide their Right Senſes, and ſtagger and reel up and down, as they did at that day, when Tythes came laſt up? And doſt thou think that thoſe Kings or others knew well what they did when they gave Tythes for the <hi>Pardoning of their Sins,</hi> or for the <hi>Health of their Souls,</hi> or for their <hi>Fathers Souls,</hi> and gone from Chriſt, the Saviour of their Souls? Or whether were they not drunk, by drinking of the Whore's Golden Cup, and beſide their Right Senſes, or at beſt, <hi>perſwaded that they ſhould merit Heaven by their own Good VVorks?</hi> And did not this make the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Strain ſo High and Rich? And whether that which a Man doth when he is drunk, or not in his Right Senſes, or doth not well know what he doth, muſt needs ſtand firm without Alteration? Can a Will ſtand good by Law when a Man is not in his Right Senſes at the time he makes it? And that this was their Caſes, I think few but <hi>Papiſts</hi> will deny.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:108218:7"/>
               <p>But ſome may Object, and ſay, <hi>VVere not many Good and VVholſome Laws in this Nation made by the</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and yet thou ſayeſt, they were in the dark, and their Examples not to be followed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, I never denyed but that there might be ſome good amongſt them, eſpecially in <hi>Temporal Things:</hi> We ſee many a Wild Drunken Man, that hath a large Underſtanding in <hi>Temporal Affairs,</hi> yet knows little of the <hi>Things of God.</hi> And it ſeems to me, that although Tythes themſelves were not, nor are not <hi>Spiritual,</hi> yet they did rather relate to the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Things,</hi> and therefore the Tryal of them was referred to the <hi>Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> until <hi>O. C.</hi> put them down, and to gratifie the Prieſts made a New Law for the Recovering of Tythes.</p>
               <p>And further, For the removing of all Scruple, I do affirm, that we do own all the Good and Wholſome Laws in the Nations that are for the Praiſe of them that do well, and for the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Evil-Doers.</p>
               <p>But we believe that no man ought to have made Laws for the <hi>Enforcing of Payment of Tythes,</hi> becauſe Chriſt the Pure Law-Giver put an End to them; but he did not end the Titles men had in their Lands: Hence I conclude, that the Titles men have, or Law by which men hold their Lands, is different from the Titles or Law by which the Prieſts or Impropriators hold their Tythes by; the one grounded upon Right Reaſon, more ancient then the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> the other a By-Law, made in the Midnight of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when men knew not well what they did, which indeed may be called, <hi>A <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping over men's Conſciences and Eſtates:</hi> For its moſt certain, men had Titles in their Lands before the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> made Laws for Payment of Tythes.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt in pag. 11. of thy Book, <hi>The Author hath not yet proved, why Laws may not be admitted for Maintenance of Miniſters, as well as Poor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which thing I have ſomething in my Heart to ſay concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108218:7"/>my Faith, or what I believe concerning that Matter: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that all Poor ought to labour, ſo much as they are able, to maintain themſelves, and not to ſpend any of God's Creatures in waſte; and what they are not able to do by their own true La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is to be made out by them that have it: and this the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God compels them that are in it to do, if there were no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Law to compel to it.</p>
               <p>And I believe the like by Miniſters, That they alſo ought to follow <hi>Paul</hi>'s Example, that is, <hi>To Labour with their Hands, that they might not be chargeable to any,</hi> 1 Theſ. 2.9. Acts 20.33, 34. Then I alſo believe, That if they be ſo called forth in the Service of the Lord, from their outward Callings, as that they cannot labour with their Hands to maintain themſelves or Families, that then <hi>they may reap Carnal Things where they have ſown Spirituals,</hi> or <hi>where they have planted a Vineyard they may eat Fruit,</hi> or <hi>where they have fed a Flock they may eat Milk.</hi> But the <hi>Jews</hi> were not to take Tythes of <hi>Strangers, the Prieſts were not to receive Wages of them they did no Work for;</hi> for that is counted unreaſonable among men, to ask Wages of them they do nothing for: But the Power of God compels them that are in it, if Need be, to adminiſter Carnal Things to thoſe that ſow unto them Spirituals; and there needs not an Outward Law to compel to it; for their Miniſtry takes Effect, and begets a Love and a Life in the Hearts of their Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; but a Dead Miniſtry begets neither Love nor Life in the Hearts of people, and ſo ſuch Miniſters are forced to cry out for an Outward Law to compel people to <hi>maintain them in Pride, and Idleneſs, and Welfare,</hi> contrary to <hi>Paul</hi>'s Exhortation to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.7, 8. who ſaid, <hi>We brought nothing into this World, and it is certain we can carry nothing out: having Food and Rayment, let us therewith be content.</hi> But theſe are not ſo <hi>content,</hi> but have <hi>great Revenues,</hi> as is well known: And are not theſe <hi>Revenues</hi> the Cauſe why ſo many men ſend their Sons to thoſe Places called <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> which makes our Nation ſwarm with ſo many <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts, that deſtroy our Corn, and would devour every Green Thing in God's Garden, and preach Peace to people in their Sins while they put into their Mouthes, and ſo cauſe them to Err,</hi> Mic. 3. <hi>and keep from the Light that gives the Knowledge of God and of his VVayes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108218:8"/>and call it Deluſion, and ſo keep people in the Erring and Straying from the VVay of God like loſt Sheep.</hi> This is one Cauſe why we can pay our <hi>Rents</hi> to <hi>Vitious Landlords</hi> or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and yet can't pay Tythes to the <hi>Prieſts;</hi> for they are Upholders of them in their Wickedneſs, if they will but ſatisfie their Ends; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are Evil Examples themſelves. Another Cauſe why we can pay our <hi>Rents</hi> to <hi>Vitious Landlords</hi> or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but cannot pay Tythes to the Prieſt is, becauſe we uſually come into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with our Land-Owners, to pay them Rent; but ſo we do not to the Prieſts, to pay them Tythes. Yea, and we can pay our Chief Rents and Taxes to the King; Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Give to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s, and to God the things that are God</hi>'s; but never commanded his Diſciples to pay or take Tythes: And were not Tythes God's? <hi>Malachi.</hi> 3. And when he ceaſed requiring of them did they not become the people's Right?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>C. N.</hi> (pag. 13.) tells us a Story of ſome Conference he had with ſome of our Perſwaſion in <hi>London</hi> ſome years ſince, whether True or Falſe I cannot tell; however, he ſeems to take Occaſion againſt the Light in our Conſciences, and ſaith, <hi>Though I grant, That the True Spirit of God cannot Deceive, yet a Lying Spirit was in all the Mouthes of</hi> Ahab<hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; and I pray you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>think it not Impoſſible that ſuch a Spirit may be in you, while yet you think you have the True.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And now ſeeing he ſayes ſo, I think it not amiſs to conſider the Fruits and the Effects of the Falſe Prophets, in whom the Lying Spirit was and is, that ſo we may know it where it appeareth now, or where it hath appeared in late years.</p>
               <p>The Falſe Prophets Encouraged <hi>Ahab,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Go up to</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth-Gilead, <hi>and Proſper; for the Lord ſhall deliver it into the Hand of the King. Michaiah</hi> the True Prophet ſaid to the King, <hi>A Lying Spirit is in the Mouthes of theſe thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and the Lord hath ſpoken Evil againſt thee,</hi> Then <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:108218:8"/>the Son of <hi>Chenaanah</hi> the Falſe Prophet came near, and ſmote <hi>Micaiah</hi> upon the Cheek, and ſaid, <hi>Which way went the Spirit of the Lord from me to ſpeak unto thee?</hi> And <hi>Micaiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>Behold thou ſhalt ſee in that Day, when thou ſhalt go into an Inner Chamber to hide thy ſelf.</hi> Then the King ſaid, <hi>Take</hi> Micaiah, <hi>and carry him back unto</hi> Ammon, <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the City, and ſay, Thus ſaith the King, Put this Fellow in the Priſon, and feed him with the Bread of Affliction, and with Water of Affliction, until I come in Peace.</hi> And <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>If thou return at all in Peace, the Lord hath not ſpoken by me. Ahab</hi> Diſguized himſelf, yet a certain man drew a Bow at a Venture, and ſmote him between the Joynt of the Harneſs, that he Dyed, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>And was not this many of your Caſes who are called <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> when ye were exalted in your Power? Did you not carry away as your own the Biſhops Lands, Gleab-Lands, and ſome Men's Free Eſtates, which was theirs by a Law, (the Crime <hi>C. N.</hi> layes to the <hi>Quakers</hi>) and exalt your ſelves in Pride by them, and forget the Lord? Of which things you cannot accuſe the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſince they were a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: For, as they were Convinced of God's Truth they left you, and bare their Teſtimony againſt you; and many of them you put in Priſon, and fed them with Bread and Water of Affliction, and ſome Dyed in Priſon by Reaſon of Hard U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: And did not thoſe Prophets in whom the Lying Spirit was, preach Peace to you in all theſe things, and encouraged you to go on, as <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Prophets did? Then did the Lord raiſe up many True Prophets, and ſent them among you, who told you, <hi>If you went on in Self-endedneſs, Pride and High-mindedneſs, ye ſhould be broken;</hi> witneſs <hi>George Fox</hi> the younger, who told you, AS YOU HAD BEATEN, HEWED AND BROKEN OTHERS, EVEN SO SHOULD YOU BE BEATEN, HEWED AND BROKEN YOUR SELVES. And did not this come to paſs? Yea, and this with much more ſtands in Print over your Heads at this day. And did not the Teachers of the Nation Encourage you to go on, and petition againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> calling the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108218:9"/>Truth <hi>Hereſie?</hi> And how did they flock to <hi>Richard Cromwell,</hi> and called him <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who ſhould carry them into the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land, which was but Tythes and Augmentations: But alas! how did the Lying Spirit deceive them, and all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved them and their Prophecying, inſomuch as that all their Harneſs would not ſave them from God's Arrow? And how did thoſe hid themſelves that had ſmitten the True Prophets, and fawn, and flatter, and walk diſguiſedly like <hi>Ahab,</hi> and ſome put on a White <hi>Surplice</hi> on the top of a Black <hi>Coat</hi> to ſave themſelves? So I hope People will ſee where this Lying Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was and is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>C. N.</hi> granteth the True Spirit cannot Deceive; ſo the <hi>Prebyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and their Prieſts may take the Lying Spirit home to themſelves, and be aſhamed that ever they Beat, Impriſoned, Whipped and Stocked the True Prophets and Servants of the Lord.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Quakers</hi> have not forgot how you carried away as your own (the Crime that is laid to them) their Pots and Pans, Hay and Corn, and put the Servants of the Lord in Priſon when they could not feed your Lying Prophets, or when they ſpoak to them in the Steeple-houſes: But the Lord brought you down, and the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Tremblers</hi> at the Word of the Lord, whom ye derided, ſtand as Witneſſes againſt you. So <hi>C. N.</hi> thou and thy Party may take this to your ſelves, to the Shame and Infamy of your whole Profeſſion: For Perſecution is a Shame and Infamy to any Profeſſion whatever And have not you <hi>Presbyterians</hi> hid your ſelves, as in an <hi>Inner Chamber,</hi> when a Storm hath come? But when the Sun hath ſhined, and the Storm been over, like <hi>Snakes</hi> ye have come out of your Holes; witneſs <hi>John Woodhouſe</hi>'s Meeting, and thine <hi>C. N.</hi> at <hi>Wortenby</hi> and at <hi>Salxelby</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire,</hi> near unto us; we have ſeen your Deviſed Service often blaſted, according to <hi>C. N.</hi>'s Belief.</p>
               <p>Again, In try 13th page thou ſayeſt, <hi>And now my Friends, if you are convinced that Tythes are none of yours, conſider, think it not ſufficient to expiate your Guilt by ſaying in your uſual Language, Let them that are free to pay Tythes pay them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:108218:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It ſeems thou thinkeſt thou haſt done ſomething, as thy words <hi>[and now my Friends]</hi> imply: But I muſt tell thee, We are convinced that we have as good right to the Tenth Part as we have to the other Nine, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe Chriſt fulfilled and put an End to that Law that gave Tythes, as before I have proved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thoſe that brought them up again were made Drunk by drinking of the Whore's Golden Cup, which was full of Abominations within, and conſequently their Examples are not to be followed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We believe, That every part and parcel of our Lands is our own, ſo far as our Deeds and Leafes make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and the Increaſe is God's, lent to us: And we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, Not to ſpend our Money for that which is not Bread, and our Labour for that which ſatisfieth not, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Chap. 55. And I muſt tell thee, We are not ſatisfied with the Prieſts, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we believe that they can give us the Bread of Life, and therefore we cannot pay them.</p>
               <p>Again, Thou biddeſt us <hi>Turn to the Light or Law in our Conſciences, and then tell thee, whether the following Concluſions muſt not neceſſarily fall, to the Shame and Infamy of our whole Profeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Before thou callſt it <hi>a Pretended Light,</hi> and now doſt thou directeſt us unto it; but it matters not what thou calleſt it; we know it to be true Light, and have turned to it: and we find that thy Concluſions do not fall upon us; but we ſee that thou art like the Perſecuting <hi>Jews,</hi> who numbred Chriſt among Thieves, and would rather have a Murderer or a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor to live then he: And what was the Cauſe of the <hi>Jews</hi> Envy againſt Chriſt? Was it not becauſe they thought in their Dark Imaginations he did ſomething contrary to their Law? It
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108218:10"/>is like if one ſhould have asked them, Who made their Law? they in their Dark Helliſh Natures would have ſaid, God gave it to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid in the four and twentieth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> and the ſixteenth Verſe, <hi>He that Blaſphemeth the Name of the Lord ſhall ſurely be put to Death.</hi> And was not this the Crime they laid to him? But God forbid that I or any true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſhould believe that theſe words concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him, ſo as to enſnare him, although they in their Dark Minds might ſo underſtand them.</p>
               <p>And <hi>C. N.</hi> What is the Cauſe that thou counteſt us more Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal then common Notorious Thieves? Is it not becauſe thou in thy Dark Imaginations thinkeſt that we do ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law: But if one ſhould ask thee, Who made thy Law thou condemneſt us by? Sayeſt thou, Such and ſuch Popiſh Kings made Laws for the Payment of Tythes, and you <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Refuſe to pay them, and therefore if Ignorance will not, nothing elſe can excuſe you before God or Man from being more Criminal then Common Notorious Thieves: And here art not thou worſe then the <hi>Jews,</hi> who pleaded a Law that was before the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> though they underſtood it wrong.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Might not</hi> Popiſh <hi>Kings do what they would with their own?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, Yes; But the Increaſe of our Labour, and Flocks and Fields, that God bleſſeth unto us this year, was not theirs to give that dyed Hundreds of Years paſt: And did not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors plead Law in all Ages againſt the Innocent, and for their <hi>Maſs</hi> and other things, and thought they went right when they had Law on their ſides? Search Scriptures and Chronicles, and ſee if it were not ſo: And do not the Perſecutors plead Law now for the taking away of Goods, and that from ſome of you called <hi>Presbyterians?</hi> And may not ſome in Ages to come upon the ſame Ground that thou pleadeſt for Tythes, plead it Right according to Law, to take away Goods if any meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to Worſhip God, if he prevent it not? Oh! that men ſhould be ſo blind to plead againſt themſelves: But thy Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſignifies a Daubing.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:108218:10"/>
               <p>In the 14th page of thy Book thou ſayeſt, <hi>Our uſual Demand, what Scripture can be produced to prove any Examples for Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Tythes to Goſpel Miniſters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſeemeſt to ſleight us for ſo doing, and what a Stir have the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> made about calling the Scriptures the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> and now if one ſpeak according to them, he is counted as one that ſeems to have neither Common Senſe nor Reaſon, or at beſt a Confident Weak Defendent; witneſs thy Reviling <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> concerning my firſt Letter, thou ſayeſt, <hi>VVe ignorantly deny Scriptures to be the Rule to try and diſtinguiſh betwixt True and Falſe Spirits:</hi> But whither art thou gone? Thy Nakedneſs of Pretence to Truth is expoſed to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure through thy own Ignorant Folly: What? are all the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for Tythes driven out of the Scriptures? And are they forced to flee to the Humane Law? <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> What is the Bible become of no uſe now? Muſt not the Pope's Authority be queſtioned? <hi>It is enough to believe as your Mother Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves.</hi> Whither are you running? Come back again, come back again for ſhame; elſe the Lord will follow you, and ye ſhall not have a Hiding-place; it is the Word of the Lord in my Heart to you all, that you may be warned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>C. N.</hi> demands of us, <hi>VVhether Scripture Example be not equal binding to people as well as Miniſters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Example of ſelling all, and laying down at Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Feet, is not binding: Acts 5.3, 4. Peter <hi>ſaid to</hi> Ananias, <hi>VVhy hath Satan filled thine Heart with a Lye to the Holy Ghoſt; whilſt it remained, was it not thine own? and after it was ſold, was it not in thine own Power?</hi> So ſee this Example was not binding; the Sin lay in Lying againſt God, in preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to give All, and yet kept a Part back. Neither do we find that this was practiſed any more.</p>
               <p>He further demands, <hi>VVhat Scripture Example we can ſhew,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108218:11"/>that any man bought Lands chargeable with Tythes, and Refuſed to pay them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not hard to gueſs from what ſpirit this Demand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth; but in the Eternal Light its ſeen to our Eyes to ariſe from that ſpirit that ſleights us for ſticking ſo cloſe to the Scriptures: I might ask him, What Scripture Example he can ſhew, that any man ſold Land chargeable with Tythes under a Goſpel-Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Again, ſeeing thou pleadeſt ſo much for <hi>Papiſts</hi> Laws, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? doſt thou own all to be Right that was brought up by the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> yea, or nay? If nay, then how or by what muſt we diſtinguiſh betwixt Right and Wrong, Good and Evil, ſeeing there is Danger of calling Good Evil, and Evil Good; and of putting Light for Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Darkneſs for Light? Anſwer this Queſtion, elſe ſtop thy Mouth forever.</p>
               <p>There are ſome frivolous Demands in thy Book, but being ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently anſwered by my Friend <hi>T. R.</hi> I ſhall paſs them by, deſiring thee to take notice of the latter-end of thy laſt Letter; thou ſayeſt, <hi>But if the Truth be not on my ſide in what I have formerly offered, or may be offered by thoſe of greater <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, then none of thoſe Concluſions are applicable againſt you; but muſt confeſſedly be returned upon me, and thoſe whoſe Cauſe I plead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Truth is not on thy ſide; for Chriſt is the Truth: and I do not know that thou haſt named either Chriſt or Scriptures in all thy firſt Letter; only at laſt thou ſayeſt, <hi>Farewell in the Name of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The name of the Lord is a Strong Tower, the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous flee unto it and are ſafe; but thou haſt not fled unto it for Safety and Strength to mannage thy Deſign; but on the contrary, haſt fled to <hi>Popiſh</hi> Authors, and ſet up their Laws above Chriſt and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and ſo haſt manifeſted thy ſelf to be more of Antichriſt then of Chriſt: So let thee and thoſe whoſe Cauſe thou pleadeſt take thy Concluſions home unto your ſelves, and according to thy words, confeſs them your Dues; for we are clear, as before is proved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:108218:11"/>
               <head>Addition.</head>
               <p>THere is a Senſe upon my Spirit concerning ſome who have their Underſtandings ſo far opened, as to ſee that Miniſters of the Goſpel ought not to receive Tythes, but they cannot tell what to ſay to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriators, becauſe they are become as Free Eſtates or Iay Poſſeſſions to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why truly Friends, if I were free to pay Tythes I could rather pay them to the Prieſt or Poor, then to the Impropriators; my Reaſons are, Becauſe they are wholely diverted from the uſe that ever they were given for; For Mark, When they were given in the Time of the Law, they were given for the Poor, Fatherlerleſs, Widdow and Prieſt, that there might not be a Beggar in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but being Ended in Chriſt, there was Collection among the Saints for the Relief of ſuch as ſtood in need: And I believe they had never come up again, had not that Midnight of Apoſtacy come up; yet when they did come up again, they were given for the Poor and Prieſt, and for the Uſe of the Church, ſo called; ſo that I believe, although the Gives of them were Blind and Dark in that Matter, and their Example not to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet it never was their Intent, That they ſhould be Bought and Sold, or become as Lay Poſſeſſions. Hence I conclude, That no man hath Right to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108218:12"/>TYTHES from Another; but when they were Ended by Chriſt, they became the Proper Right of the Donors, as was the Reſt of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>I Have a few words to ſay in Love to all thoſe that ſend their Sons to thoſe places called Univerſities, with an Intent to make them Miniſters; <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they think they buy the Gift of God or nay? If yea, then are not they in the Gall of Bitterneſs, that think, that the Gift of God can be bought for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney? <hi>Acts</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> If it be not the Gift of God, then what is it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether they that Sell the Gift of God for Money, are not as bad as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> the Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, who thought it might be bought for Money?</p>
               <p>And further, Be it known unto you all, The Lord will not have Miniſters of your Choice; but he will have Miniſters of his own chuſing, and he will ſet up his School on the Top of all your Schools and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, namely, the Teachings of his own Spirit in the Hearts of his People; for he is as Able as ever he was to chuſe poor Tradeſ-men, and to fill them with his Spirit, Power and Wiſdom, and to ſend them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108218:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>forth to preach the Everlaſting Goſpel, as ever he was, though ſome may ſay, <hi>Is it not the Carpentor's Son, whoſe Father and Mother we know?</hi> I might produce many Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to prove that God and Chriſt often times choſe ſuch as were Unlearned, and little eſteemed in the Eyes of the World (ſee the firſt of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> verſe one, and <hi>Acts</hi> four, verſe thirteen) that no Fleſh might glory in his Preſence: And now is the Lord fulfilling his Promiſes who ſaid, <hi>In the laſt days I will pour out of my Spirit upon all Fleſh, upon my Hand-Maids I will pour out in thoſe dayes of my Spirit, and they ſhall Propheſie: I will put my Law in their inward Parts, and write it in their Hearts,</hi> Jeremiah 32. Joel 2. Act Therefore all ye that ſleight the Lord's Work at this day, which he is doing in and among his People, betware, leſt that come upon you which is ſpoken in the Prophets, Behold ye Deſpiſers, and wonder and periſh; I work a Work in your day, a Work which ye ſhall in no wiſe believe though a Man declare it unto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:108218:13"/>
               <head>A Copy of a Letter ſent to <hi>CLEMENT NEDHAM:</hi> Whereunto is added a ſhort Poſtſcript.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>C. Nedham,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Find Drawings in the Bowels of Love to write unto thee; and deſire thee, that thou wouldſt imploy thy Wiſdom, Strength ad Pretious Time in and for the Uſe and ſervice of thy Creator, and againſt Oppreſſion that the poor People groan under, even as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did under <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Task-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and not to ſpend it in and for the Uſe and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Proud Prieſts and Impropriators, Beaſt, Whore and Falſe Prophet, except thou are able to prove, They are of God, and their Wages Right, according to his Law, leſt thou proveſt a Servant to the Devil; for he is the Root from whence all Evil ſprings, and thou canſt not ſerve two Maſters.</p>
               <p>But if thou wilt perſiſt in Oppoſing the Truth, and the Requirings of God's Spirit in the Hearts of his People; be it known unto thee, That New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which is coming down from God out of Heaven, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared as a Bride adorned for her Husband which thou writeſt againſt, and ſpendeſt thy pretious Time to oppoſe, and calleſt her Light a <hi>Pretended Light</hi>) will prove a Burdenſom ſtone too heavy for thee to Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
               <p>And now it is in my Heart to put thee in mind of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108218:13"/>thy Unhanſome and Unchriſtian-like Dealings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Time thou didſt ſend thy Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to us, was when Friends of <hi>Clauſon</hi> (where thou didſt direct thy Letter) were under Sufferings and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Threatnings by <hi>John Reay</hi> Propriator of the ſame Town, whoſe Envy was and is beyond the Bounds of <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> And here thou ſeemeſt to add Affliction to the Afflicted, and to ſtrengthen the Hands of Evil-Doers. Again, After thou hadſt ſent thy firſt Letter I ſent one in Love to thee, for that End that thy Underſtanding might be opened to ſee the Rice and Ground of Tythes, and what Spirit brought them up; hoping a Word to the Wiſe might have been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: But inſtead of accepting my Love, thou vilifiedſt me with Reviling Words, as one that ſeemed to have neither common Senſe nor Reaſon, and ſaidſt, <hi>Thou waſt unwilling that the Nakedneſs of our Pretence to Truth ſhould be expoſed to Cenſures through the Ignorance, Folly and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſoweak a Defendent:</hi> And here thou didſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thy Pride, as if thou thought ſcorn to meddle with me; much like <hi>Goliah</hi> the <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> who defyed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and diſdained <hi>David,</hi> and then brought forth another Monſter more Odious then the firſt; and we being ſilent a while thou didſt put them all in Print, and for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther End, as I can ſee, but to render us Odious to the whole Nation, and to open a Gap for further Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For conſider, After thy many Arguments, and pleading Popiſh Laws, thou draweſt thy Concluſions, <hi>That if Ignorance will not, nothing elſe can excuſe us before God or Man from being more Criminal then Common Notorious Thieves:</hi> Further, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Malefactors do or may ſuffer Death by Law for ſtealing things of ſmall account; but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108218:14"/>your Robbery</hi> (ſayeſt thou) <hi>is of great Value; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Laws are very favourable towards you.</hi> A ſad Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence! Were ever ſuch Concluſions drawn againſt an Innocent People? Truly when I read them I could not but ſay, There was a Snare laid for our Lives; and it brought to my Remembrance the Cruelty of <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Perſecutors: But how Juſt thy Charge is, I hope is or will in due time be made manifeſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From thy True Friend</hi> John Wilsford</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who could be glad to ſee a perſecuting</hi> Saul <hi>become a Preaching</hi> Paul.</p>
               <p>I have ſomething further to ſay in anſwer to thy Book, which if I do hear thou art not ſatisfied, in due time it may come forth, ſeeing thou haſt made my Name publick to the Nation.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Broughton, <date>
                        <hi>the 3d of the 8th Moneth,</hi> 1673.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>J. W.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Theſe words above written were delivered into the hands of <hi>C. N.</hi> the 5th Day of the 8th Moneth.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:108218:14"/>
               <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>READER,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>FOr thy better Satisfaction, or leſt thou ſhouldſt think I have not done fairly in mentioning ſome things that are done and paſt; do but conſider <hi>C. N</hi>'s Wicked Charge and Unhanſome Dealings towards me and the reſt of my Friends; weight them in the Ballance of Equity, and then ſee if I could do any leſs then I have done; or whether I have done any more then to lay the Load on the Right Horſe. Further conſider, That notwithſtanding Chriſt Jeſus ſo loved the World as that he laid down his Life for it, yet when the <hi>Jews</hi> roſe up in Envy againſt him, he told them how they killed the Prophets, and ſtoned them that were ſent unto them, as may be ſeen at large <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. And likewiſe when the Jews roſe up in Envy againſt <hi>Peter,</hi> he told them how they crucified and ſlew the Lord of Life, as thou mayſt ſee at large in the <hi>Acts,</hi> Chap. 2, 3, 4. And <hi>John</hi> ſaid, Rev. 18.6, 7. <hi>Reward her, even as ſhe rewarded you, double unto her double, according to her Works.</hi> Some may ſay, <hi>Art thou pleading for a Carnal Weapon?</hi> I anſwer, Nay; the Saints Weapons are not Carnal, but Spiritual; the Lamb's Sword proceedeth out of his Mouth; if any man have an Ear to hear, let him hear, here is the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Patience of Saints, He that killeth with the Sword, muſt with the Sword be killed. And ſo I leave, deſiring every one to mind the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which gives a true Underſtanding of the Myſteries of his Kingdom.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
